Guide to the James Buchanan Duke Papers, 1777-1999 and undated RL.00001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Buchanan Duke papers
1777-1999 and undated, bulk 1890s-1930s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925
RL.00001
33 Linear Feet
James B. Duke (1856-1925) was a tobacco manufacturer, industrialist, and philanthropist of Durham, North Carolina, and New York City and the youngest son of Washington Duke. He was also father to Doris Duke, who inherited a considerable portion of her father's estate at an early age and became known as "the richest girl in the world." James B. Duke's major business concerns included W. Duke, Sons and Company; American Tobacco Company; British American Tobacco Company; and Southern Power Company. His philanthropic activities included endowments of Trinity College (later renamed Duke University) and Lincoln Hospital of Durham, North Carolina. In December 1924, Duke established the Duke Endowment, a permanent trust fund whose beneficiaries include Duke University and three other institutions of higher education, rural churches, non-profit hospitals, and child care institutions throughout North and South Carolina. The collection was compiled from various sources and includes: correspondence; business, legal, and financial papers; estate and inheritance records; printed materials; miscellaneous materials; architectural drawings and blueprints; and pictures chiefly relating to the businesses, enterprises and philanthropy of James Buchanan Duke in North Carolina, South Carolina, New York, New Jersey, and Québec, Canada. About one-half of the collection documents the administration of his estate. Subject areas represented include: American Tobacco Company; British American Tobacco Company; Southern Power Company; business; finance; aspects of the tobacco industry, including automation, marketing and taxation; hydroelectric power; textile mills; charitable works; architectural planning and interior decoration; genealogy of branches of the Duke family; inheritance and succession; estate taxation; and legal procedure for wills, inheritance and business.
circa 24,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Includes fragile letterbooks and other volumes that require consultation with staff regarding safe handling.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Buchanan Duke Papers were transferred to the Special Collections Department from various sources beginning in 1957 and continuing through 1990. Funds from The Duke Endowment supported the reprocessing of this collection from 1991 to 1992.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1856, Dec. 23 Born, Orange County, N.C.
1870s Attended Eastman Business College, Poughkeepsie, N.Y.
1878 Full partner in newly incorporated W. Duke, Sons and Company
ca. 1883 President, W. Duke, Sons and Company
1884 Moved to New York, N.Y.
Negotiated contract with Bonsack Machine Company for use of cigarette manufacturing machine
1890 Organized The American Tobacco Company
1902, Sept. 27 Signed agreement with British tobacco manufacturers to form British-American Tobacco Company
1904, Sept. Married Lillian McCreedy ( divorced 1906)
1905 Established Southern Power Company with Benjamin N. Duke and George W. Watts
1907, July 23 Married Nanaline Holt Inman
1911, May Dissolution of the American Tobacco Company ordered by the United States Supreme Court
1912, Nov. 22 Daughter, Doris Duke, born
ca. 1915 Purchased hydroelectric power resources on Saguenay River, Quebec, Canada
1915-1919 Began plans for a philanthropic trust to serve educational and other institutions in North Carolina and South Carolina
1917 Duke Farms Company, Somerville, N.J., incorporated
ca. 1923 Duke-Price Power Company established
1924, Dec. 11 Signed indentures establishing The Duke Endowment and The Doris Duke Trust
1925, Oct. 10 Died, New York, N.Y.
1928, May 21 Final determination by State of New Jersey Court in the Matter of the Estate of James B. Duke, Deceased
1930 Remains removed to the Memorial Chapel of Duke University Chapel
1934, June 18 Estate of James B. Duke liquidated
1961 Widow, Nanaline H. Duke, died
Collection Overview
The papers of James Buchanan Duke have been collected from various sources over time and span the years 1777 to 1999, although the bulk of the material dates from the 1890s to the mid-1930s. The collection is divided into 7 series: Correspondence, Business Papers, Legal Papers, Financial Papers, Estate Papers, Miscellaneous, and Pictures. About one half of the collection documents the administration of the Estate of James B. Duke, Deceased, including legal proceedings stemming from claims made against the estate. The remainder of the collection deals largely with businesses and financial investments, mainly through the Business Papers, Financial Papers, and Estate Papers Series. To a lesser extent, aspects of Duke's philanthropy are documented through the Financial Papers, Correspondence, and Legal Papers, while personal topics are concentrated in the Picture Series, Miscellaneous Series, and Correspondence Series. Subject areas represented in the collection include: the tobacco and hydroelectric power industries; business and finance; philanthropy; genealogy on branches of the Duke family; inheritance; legal procedure; architecture and interior decoration; and, to a lesser degree, family life.
Since brother Benjamin Newton Duke participated in many of the same businesses and enterprises as James B. Duke, items of his business correspondence and documents related to his investments and domestic expenditures are also found throughout the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: Correspondence, Business Papers, Legal Papers, Financial Papers, Estate Papers, Miscellaneous, and Pictures.
Related Materials
Artifacts and Relics Collection, 1830s-[ongoing] (Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Benjamin Newton Duke Papers, 1834-1984, bulk 1884-1929 (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Board of Trustees Records, 1860-ongoing (Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Doris Duke papers, 1798-2003 (bulk 1930-1999) (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Duke Family papers, 1885-1992 (bulk 1892-1927) (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Duke Family papers on the Duke Farms residence, 1859-2004 and undated (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
W. Duke, Sons & Co. Advertising Materials, 1880-1910 (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Washington Duke Papers, 1764-1987 (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
William Preston Few Records and Papers, 1814 - 1971 and undated (bulk 1911-1940) (Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Semans Family Papers, 1878-2008 and undated (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Inheritance and succession -- North Carolina; Inheritance and succession -- New Jersey; Inheritance and transfer tax -- North Carolina; Architectural drawing -- New Jersey; Architectural drawing -- New York; Architectural drawing -- North Carolina; Tobacco industry -- New York; Procedure (Law) -- New Jersey; Inheritance and transfer tax -- New Jersey; Hydroelectric power plants -- Québec (Province); Hydroelectric power plants -- North Carolina; Tobacco -- Marketing; Finance -- United States; Tobacco -- Taxation -- Law and legislation -- United States; Businessmen -- North Carolina -- Durham; Cigarette industry -- Automation.; Interior decoration -- United States.; Tobacco industry -- North Carolina; Philanthropists -- North Carolina; Hydroelectric power plants -- South Carolina; Businessmen -- New York; Textile industry -- North Carolina; Duke family; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925 -- Estate; British American Tobacco Company; Duke, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Newton); American Tobacco Company; Duke, Doris; Duke family -- Genealogy.; Duke Endowment; Southern Power Company (Charlotte, N.C.)
- Correspondence, 1880-1940 and undated; 1900-1911; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically, with loose correspondence first.
  Scope and Contents
  Primarily personal and business letters and telegrams received and sent by James B. Duke or his agents, with letters sent or received by Benjamin N. Duke scattered throughout the correspondence. Letters related to philanthropic ventures, including contributions to Trinity College (later Duke University) and requests for donations and other forms of aid, are also present. Since the series includes several bound letterbooks, the correspondence was not divided between personal and business subjects. Richard B. Arrington, a secretary and agent for Benjamin N. Duke and James B. Duke, is the principal correspondent on behalf of James B. Duke in the letterbook dated from August 1, 1900 to January 30, 1906. Alexander H. Sands, another secretary and agent for Benjamin N. Duke and James B. Duke, is the principal correspondent on behalf of James B. Duke in the letterbook dated from February 20, 1920 to January 17, 1923. Major correspondents include Lida Duke Angier (Mrs. J.C. Angier), Richard B. Arrington, W.T. Blackwell, Bettie Roney Dailey (Mrs. John C. Dailey), Benjamin Newton Duke, Washington Duke, George W. Hill, Maude Duke Karnes, William R. Perkins, and Alexander H. Sands.
  Loose correspondence dated after 1923 is primarily concerned with Benjamin N. Duke' s effort to identify and, in some cases, financially assist first and second cousins on the Roney side of the family. The main correspondents in this matter are Benjamin N. Duke, Bettie Roney Dailey, Alexander H. Sands, and Edna L. Vaughan.
  - 1880, 1 items (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    James B. Duke to Benjamin N. Duke and Sarah P. Duke, 18 August 1880, regarding family trip to Tennessee.
  - 1892-1895, 13 items (Box 1)
  - 1896-1897, 11 items (Box 1)
  - 1898-1899, 13 items (Box 1)
  - 1900-1902, 22 items (Box 1)
  - 1903, 16 items (Box 1)
  - 1904-1905, 73 items (Box 1)
    Includes telegrams from Benjamin N. Duke to James B. Duke regarding Washington Duke's health; condolence letters and telegrams to James B. Duke on the occasion of Washington Duke's death
  - 1907, 3 items (Box 1)
    Includes instructions from James B. Duke to Benjamin N. Duke for disbursements to Trinity College in 1907
  - 1910-1911, 3 items (Box 1)
  - 1913, 8 items (Box 1)
    Includes letter acknowledging receipt of a contribution to the Trinity College endowment; correspondence related to the Conservatory of Music lot in Durham, NC
  - 1914, 9 items (Box 1)
    Chiefly letters regarding Execution against the wages of Eustace Crocker (employee) (see also Legal Papers: Agreements, Court Records, Indentures, 1897-1925); letter from Trinity College alumnus to James B. Duke
  - 1915-1916, 2 items (Box 1)
    Report from W. P. Few and Trinity College Board of Trustees on the distrubtion of the J.B. Duke's fund for "worn-out" Methodist preachers; J.B. Duke to Frank Vanderlip, requesting he act as the 1916 Trinity College Commencement speaker
  - 1917-1918, 8 items (Box 1)
    J.B. Duke to Alex. H. Sands requesting alteration to Doris Duke Trust; correspondence with National Americana Society re: chapter on the Duke family in "Annals of American Families" (see Miscellaneous Series: Printed Materials: Duke family history (oversize))
  - 1919, 1922, 2 items (Box 1)
  - 1924 (Box 1)
    Mainly correspondence related to Benjamin N. Duke's search for relations; includes resolution from Mecklenburg Alumni of Trinity College supporting the change of the institution's name to Duke University
  - 1925, 4 folders (Box 1)
    Mainly correspondence related to Benjamin N. Duke's search for relations; includes confirmation of transfer of stock from James B. Duke to Duke University for building fund (May 29-June 1, 1925); letter from Benjamin N. Duke to Sarah P. Duke regarding James B. Duke's final illness and treatment (September 26, 1925)
  - 1940, 2 items (Box 1)
    Letter from A. H. Sands to R. L. Flowers, April 1940
  - Nanaline Duke, undated; 3 items (Box 1)
    Two letters addressed to W. R. Perkins, one page of notes
  - Letterbook: 1900, August 1-1906, January 30, 1 Volumes (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Fragile—please ask for staff assistance in handling this item.
  - Letterbook: 1906, January 31-1908, November 18, 1906-1908; 1 Volumes (Box 3)
  - Letterbook: 1908, November 18-1909, December 6, 1908-1909; 1 Volumes (Box 4)
  - Letterbook: 1909, April 12- 1911, December 18, 1909-1911; 1 Volumes (Box 5)
  - Letterbook: 1920, February-1923, December, 1920-1923; 1 Volumes (Box 6)
- Business Papers, 1884-1941 (bulk 1910s-1920s); 2
  Arranged by name of the business and type of material, then chronologically.
  Partial documentation for businesses that James B. Duke owned or had investment interests in, including the American Tobacco Company, British-American Tobacco Company, Duke Farms Company, Orlando Water Power Corporation, Quebec Development Company, Southern Power Company, W. Duke, Sons and Company and other businesses. Contains correspondence; minutes and corporate records; financial records including ledger books, journals, cashbooks, voucher records, vouchers and cancelled checks; stock certificates; contracts; maps of power transmission lines; and financial worksheets.
  The most complete records are for Duke Farms Company in Somerville, New Jersey (apparently a holding company), including documentation for Piedmont Electro-Chemical Company, Southern Power Company, Orlando Water Power Company, and other Duke-owned businesses. Also documented are negotiations between James B. Duke on behalf of W. Duke, Sons and Company and The American Tobacco Company, and representatives of the Bonsack Machine Company regarding the cigarette-rolling machinery that contributed to the dominance of Duke family's tobacco businesses.
  For W. Duke, Sons and Company material dated after its merger with The American Tobacco Company, see The American Tobacco Company. Correspondence with The Bonsack Machine Company is filed with the W. Duke, Sons and Company correspondence and in The American Tobacco Company letterbook.
  - Accounts (miscellaneous), 1922 1927; 4 items (Box 7)
    Worksheets of accounts owed James B. Duke by Orlando Water Power Corporation, Southern Investment Co. of New Jersey, Duke Farms Company; Analysis of profits and loss for Orlando Water Power Company for the years 1916-1920
  - American Tobacco Company: Correspondence, 1892-1894; 3 items (Box 7)
    Includes copy of American Tobacco Company consignment agreement
  - American Tobacco Company: Correspondence, 1897-1900; 14 items (Box 7)
    Includes 10 letters written by Richard Battle and various Colorado grocers related to the dismissal of Battle from American Tobacco Company (June-July 1898)
  - American Tobacco Company: Correspondence: Letterbook, 1894 July 31-1904 October 10 (Box 7)
    Alphabetical index at beginning of book. Chiefly outgoing correspondence from J.B. Duke, and, to a lesser extent, B. N. Duke and R. Arrington; includes communication with the directors of the Bonsack Machine Co.
  - American Tobacco Company: Financial, 1891 1895 1902-1909 1911 (Box 7)
  - American Tobacco Company: Financial: Stocks, bonds, scrip, 1890-1913 (Box 7)
  - American Tobacco Company: By-laws, circa 1890 (Box 7)
  - American Tobacco Company: Corporate mergers: Continental Tobacco Co., Consolidated Tobacco Co., 1904 (Box 7)
  - American Tobacco Company: Leases of property from W. Duke, Sons and Company, 1890 (Box 7)
  - American Tobacco Company: Testimony, John R. Miller, et als, complainant and The American Tobacco Co., defendants, 1895 January 2 (Box 7)
    Testimony of George Arents, treasurer of the American Tobacco Co.
  - American Tobacco Company: United States vs. American Tobacco Company et al., subpoena, 1908 March 11 (Box 7)
  - American Tobacco Company: United States vs. American Tobacco Company et al., testimony by J. B. Duke (pp. 3276-3514), 1908; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Anderson Traction Company: Acquisition, 1909 (Box 7)
    Correspondence related to the purchase of the Anderson Traction Company by a syndicate that included James B. Duke and Benjamin N. Duke
  - British-American Tobacco Company, 1902; 1932; 3 items (Box 7)
    Includes notes for telegrams sent by James B. Duke to Washington Duke and Col. Payne; illustrated menu for dinner given by James B. Duke to the British-American Tobacco Co. directors in London
  - British-American Tobacco Company: B.A.T. Bulletin, 1925 October (Box 7)
    Newsletter with James B. Duke commemoration
  - British-American Tobacco Company: Chairmanship of the Board of Directors: James B. Duke, 1912 April; 3 items (Box 7)
  - British-American Tobacco Company: Financial: Accounts with J.B. Duke, 1905-1906; 1910; 1913-1914; undated; 10 items (Box 7)
  - British-American Tobacco Company: Financial: Analysis of vouchers, journal entries, 1914 May-1914 June (Box 7)
  - British-American Tobacco Company: Financial: stocks, bonds, warrants, 1912-1913; 1920-1921; 1926; 14 items (Box 7)
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Corporate records: Certificate of Dissolution, 1929 March 27; 1933 February 3; 2 items (Box 8)
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Corporate records, 1924-1929; 1941; 1 Volumes (Box 8)
    Includes Certificate of Incorporation, bylaws
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Journal, 1924 September-1929 April; 1 Volumes (Box 8)
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Ledger, 1924-1929; 1 Volumes (Box 8)
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Cashbook, 1924 November-1929 March; 1 Volumes (Box 8)
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Vouchers, 1924-1929 (Box 8)
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Stocks, 1924-1929 (Box 8)
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Trial balances, 1925 October - 1929 (Box 8)
  - Buchanan Investment Corporation: Check stubs nos. 1-27; Cancelled checks, 1924-1929 (Box 9)
  - Duke Farms Company: Correspondence, 1917-1930 (Box 9)
  - Duke Farms Company: Minutes: Certificate of Incorporation (copy), 1922; Certificate of Dissolution, 1927 (Box 9)
  - Duke Farms Company: Minutes, 1922-1931; 1941; 1 Volumes (Box 9)
    In addition to minutes of Board of Directors meetings, includes copies of Certificate of Incorporation; indenture of sale to Doris Duke (1927); Opinion, Doris Duke v. Executors of the Estate of James B. Duke; Inventory of tangible personal property of Duke Farms Co.
  - Duke Farms Company: Ledger, 1922-1931; 1 Volumes (Box 10)
  - Duke Farms Company: Journal, 1922 December-1931 January; 1 Volumes (Box 11)
  - Duke Farms Company: Cashbook, 1922 December-1931 January; 1 Volumes (Box 12)
  - Duke Farms Company: Vouchers, 1922 December-1925 June; 8 folders (Box 9)
  - Duke Farms Company: Vouchers, 1925 July-1931; 7 folders (Box 13)
  - Duke Farms Company: Cancelled checks, 1922-1930; 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Duke Farms Company: Accounts, 1906-1929 (Box 13)
  - Duke Farms Company: Accounts (oversize), 1922 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Duke Farms Company: Appraisal of real and personal property, 1925, December 15; Recast balance sheet...as of 1925, October 10 (Box 13)
  - Duke Farms Company: Assignments (Southern Investment Co. of Canada to Orlando Water Power Corp., 1916; Frank C. Schmitz to Orlando Water Power Corp., 1920; Orlando Water Power to Duke Farms, 1922; Duke Farms to Southern Power Co., 1927), 1916-1927 (Box 13)
  - Duke Farms Company: Bill of Sale: Duke Farms Co. to Doris Duke, 1927 (Box 13)
  - Duke Farms Company: Financial statements: worksheets (oversize), 1916-1925 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Duke Farms Company: Federal Income Tax, 1918; 1919; 1926; 1927; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Duke Farms Company: Federal Income Tax, 1928; 1929; 1930; 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Duke Farms Company: Income taxes (oversize), 1918-1919 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Duke Farms Company: Loan with National City Bank, New York, 1923-1925 (Box 14)
  - Duke Farms Company: Staffing levels, 1917-1927 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Financial statements: worksheets (oversize), 1916-1925 (Box 74)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Austrian, 1917-1925 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Brazilian, 1915-1925 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Canadian, 1918-1921 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, English, 1912-1925 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, French, 1912-1925 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, German, 1916-1925 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Hungarian, 1916-1925 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Italian, 1913-1923 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Italian (oversize), 1913-1920 (Box 74)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Norwegian, 1916-1926 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Spanish, 1914-1926 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Spanish, published notices, 1919 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Swedish, 1916-1925 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Patents, Swiss, 1917-1925 (Box 14)
  - Orlando Water Power Corporation: Plan (blueprint) showing transmission line (oversize) (Box 74)
  - Quebec Development Company, 1914-1924 (Box 14)
  - Quebec Development Company: Agreements involving Price Brothers and Company, Ltd., Duke-Price Power, and Orlando Water Power Corp., 1914-1920 (Box 14)
  - Quebec Development Company: George D. Haskell vs. Aluminum Company of America et al., 1929 (Box 14)
  - Quebec Development Company: Transmission lines in Canada (oversize) (Box 74)
  - Southern Investment Company of Canada, 1913; 1916 (Box 14)
  - Southern Investment Company of Delaware and Southern Investment Company of New Jersey: Financial statements, 1912-1922 (Box 14)
    Includes miscellaneous multi-year financial analyses, such as accounts with J.B. Duke and dividends paid
  - Southern Investment Company of Delaware and Southern Investment Company of New Jersey: Financial statements: worksheets (oversize), 1912-1922 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Southern Power Company: American Trust Company bonds, 1914-1922 (Box 14)
  - Southern Power Company: Maps of transmission system in North Carolina and South Carolina (oversize), 1922; undated; 3 maps (Box 73)
    Two maps also show locations of textile mills
  - Textile mills: correspondence, stocks, loans, 1892-1935 (Box 14)
  - Union Cotton Bagging Corporation, 1912-1923 (Box 14)
  - W. Duke, Sons and Company: Contract: Louis Bastet (tobacco paper), 1885; 1 items (Box 14)
  - W. Duke, Sons and Company: Correspondence, 1889; 1 items (Box 14)
    J.B. Duke to B. N. Duke, 29 September 1889
  - W. Duke, Sons and Company: Correspondence: Bonsack Machine Co., 1884-1889 (Box 15)
  - W. Duke, Sons and Company: Correspondence: Bonsack Machine Co., 1885-1889 (Box 15)
  - W. Duke, Sons and Company: Correspondence: Bonsack Machine Co. (letters received from D. B. Strouse and P. A. Krise) [Books 1-3], 1885 October-1889 December; undated 1885; 3 folders (Box 15)
    Originally bound in three letterbooks. Table of contents included for each letterbook. Book 1 contains three letters from Jas. A Bonsack to J.B. Duke.
  - W. Duke, Sons and Company: Correspondence: Bonsack Machine Co., 1890 June (Box 15)
    D.B. Strouse to J.B. Duke, June 28, 1890 (2 copies)
- Legal Papers, 1878-1926 and undated (bulk 1910s-1925); 3
  Arranged by subject, then chronologically.